Guide to the James Fenimore Cooper Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Personal Papers, 1792-1975; Series III; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  The series contains various documents relating to Cooper's personal life and writing career. The Diaries and Notebooks subseries records Cooper's travels, for example, while in Holland, Switzerland, France, and Italy, as well as notebooks on legal matters such as his "Copy Right Book" and accusations against Horace H. Comstock, with whom Cooper invested in real estate. Cooper's memorandum books, which chronicle his daily life predominantly between 1832 and 1835, provide insight into his activities and thoughts, including his impressions of what he was reading.
  A number of court cases involving Cooper, the majority of which were libel suits, can be found in Legal Records. Briefs, court records, lawyer's notes, witnesses' testimony, and other documents provide evidence of Cooper's litigious relationship with the press. In many cases his nephew Richard Cooper served as his lawyer. This subseries also contains copyright documents filed by Cooper's family members following his death.
  Cooper's account books, located in Financial Records, along with bills, accounts, and receipts, reveal his personal finances. His brief partnership with Charles T. Dering in the whaling business is documented in an account book for the whaling vessel Union. His accounts with printers and publishers are also included in the Financial Records subseries and provide insight into Cooper's income and various costs associated with printing his writings. Extensive bills, accounts, and receipts, dating from 1812 to 1851, capture everyday realities of the Cooper family. Financial material for the Coopers' son, Paul, are also included in the subseries.
  The Other Papers subseries contains material pertaining to Cooper and his family members, ranging from documents granting appointments to a recipe for yeast. Among the papers are a series of warrants appointing Cooper to several military positions, from midshipman to paymaster and quartermaster, within the navy. In addition, Cooper's appointment as consul of Lyons, France, along with his move to Europe, is chronicled in various official letters, visas, travel documents, a passport, and calling cards.
  The Printed Material subseries includes a number of printed items such as maps and engravings of New York City and asylums. The Clippings subseries consists of newspaper clippings with Cooper's letters to the editor as well as commentary by the press on his writings and libel suits.
  - Diaries and Notebooks
    - Diary of "Holland and Switzerland, France and Italy", 1828 July - 1829 October (Box 23, Folder 480)
    - "Journal of a Tour in 1832", 1832-1833 (Box 23, Folder 481)
    - "Memorandum Book", 1835 (Box 23, Folder 482)
    - Daily memorandum book, 1848 (Box 23, Folder 483)
    - "Copy Right Book", 1842 February 19 (Box 23, Folder 484)
    - "Account of Charges Against Horace H. Comstock, in Managing Property Given to Me as Security", 1830-1850 (Box 23, Folder 485)
  - Legal Records
    - Warrant of attorney issued to an unnamed person to appear for Cooper in the suit of Luther Bradish, partially filled out in an unidentified handwriting, and signed by Cooper, 1806 May 22 (Box 24, Folder 486)
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. Andrew M. Barber, 1839 (Box 24, Folder 487-488)
      Court documents, signed by R. Cooper, as attorney for the plaintiff (James Fenimore Cooper) and Morehouse and Lathrop, attorneys for the defendent (Andrew M. Barber) for libel suit argued at the New York Supreme Court
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. Park Benjamin, 1840-1841 (Box 24, Folder 489)
      Court documents, signed by R. Cooper, as attorney for the plaintiff (James Fenimore Cooper) and Fayerweather and Edwards, attorneys for the defendent (Park Benjamin) for libel suit argued at the New York Supreme Court
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. Horace Greeley and Thomas McElrath, 1841-1845 (Box 24, Folder 490-491)
      Court documents, signed by R. Cooper, as attorney for the plaintiff (James Fenimore Cooper) and William H. Seward and Peter Clark, attorneys for the defendents (Horace Greeley and Thomas McElrath) for libel suit argued at the New York Supreme Court
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. Sidney Ketchum, 1848 August 8 (Box 24, Folder 492)
      Summons and complaint of James Fenimore Cooper served on Sidney Ketchum for non-payment of a promissary note, signed by Richard Cooper as attorney for James Fenimore Cooper
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. Rufus Northway, 1841-1842 (Box 24, Folder 493)
      Court documents, signed by R. Cooper, as attorney for the plaintiff (James Fenimore Cooper) and Spencer and Kernan, attorneys for the defendents (Rufus Northway) for libel suit argued at the New York Supreme Court
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. James S. Sandford with George C. Gibbs and James Wright Gordon, 1845-1851 (Box 24, Folder 494)
      Lawyers' letters, court documents, and other material concerning suit against the endorsers of a promissory note made by Sidney Ketchum. Court documents signed by R. Cooper, as attorney for the plaintiff (James Fenimore Cooper) and Mortimer Porter, attorney for the defendents for suit argued at the New York Supreme Court
    - Robert Sedgwick vs. James Fenimore Cooper, undated (Box 24, Folder 495)
      Holograph outline of case of bond interest suit argued at the New York Supreme Court
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. William L. Stone, 1840-1842 (Box 25, Folder 496-497)
      Lawyers' letters, court documents, and other material concerning libel suit brought against William L. Stone as editor of the Commercial Advertiser for remarks on Cooper's The History of the Navy of the United States of America. Court documents signed by R. Cooper, as attorney for the plaintiff (James Fenimore Cooper) and Hiram Ketcham, attorney for the defendent (William L. Stone) for suit argued at the New York Supreme Court
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. William L. Stone, 1840 (Box 25, Folder 498)
      Newspaper account of libel suit, James Fenimore Cooper vs. William L. Stone, clipped and mounted, with Cooper's handwritten notes and comments
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. William L. Stone, 1843-1844 (Box 25, Folder 499)
      Documents relating to case of William L. Stone, plaintiff in error vs. James Fenimore Cooper, defendant in error. Suit in the court for the correction of errors to Cooper's charges in libel against Stone. Court documents signed by R. Cooper, as attorney for the defendant (James Fenimore Cooper) and Spencer and Kernan, attorneys for the plaintiff (William L. Stone)
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. Rensselaer Waterman, 1847 (Box 25, Folder 500)
      Documents relating to several cases of Cooper vs. Waterman, including suits fought in the Otsego court of common pleas and court for the correction of errors. Court documents signed by R. Cooper, as attorney for the defendant (James Fenimore Cooper) and Starkweather and Field, attorneys for the plaintiff (Rensselaer Waterman)
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs. Thurlow Weed, Benjamin Hoffman and Andrew White, 1841-1842 (Box 25, Folder 501-502)
      Court records, lawyers' letters, and other documents for libel suit. Court documents signed by R. Cooper, as attorney for the plaintiff (James Fenimore Cooper) and Henry G. Wheaton, Parmelee and Loveridge as attorneys for the defendants for suit argued at the New York Supreme Court
    - James Fenimore Cooper vs.William White and Visscher Ten Eyck, 1845 (Box 25, Folder 503)
      Documents relating to libel suit between Cooper and White and Ten Eyck, including plaintiff's pleas drawn up by Richard Cooper as plaintiff's attorney and defendant's pleas drawn up by Beach and Morgan, attorneys, and by William H. Seward, counsel for the defendants
    - The People vs. James Watson Webb, 1838-1843 (Box 25, Folder 504)
      Briefs, court records, lawyers notes, and other documents concerning the Effingham libels of James Fenimore Cooper. Some documents signed by S. Crippen, district attorney.
      Includes printed extract from a chapter of Home As Found showing the context from which the Courier 's extract was taken
    - Frederick T. Tiffany vs. James Fenimore Cooper
      - Notebook with brief handwritten accounts of various persons connected with the suit, circa 1845 (Box 26, Folder 505)
      - Briefs, court records, lawyer's notes, witnesses' testimony, and other documents, on a case of trespass, signed by Richard Cooper as attorney for the defendant (James Fenimore Cooper) and by Alfred H. Corning, attorney for the plaintiff (Frederick T. Tiffany), 1845-1848 (Box 26, Folder 506-508)
      - State of New York Supreme Court: Frederick T. Tiffany vs. James F. Cooper Demurrer Book (New York: Searing and Cooke, 1847) with marginal notes by Richard Cooper (Box 26, Folder 509)
        Alfred H. Corning, attorney for the plaintiff; Richard Cooper, attorney for defendent
        Includes handwritten documents
    - Oliver Williams vs. James Fenimore Cooper, 1839 (Box 26, Folder 510)
      Pleas, lawyers' notes, and summary of the case as settled in July 1839. Documents signed by Richard Cooper as attorney for the defendant (James Fenimore Cooper) and by L.J. Walworth attorney for the plaintiff in a slander suit
    - Insurance policies, 1825-1848 (Box 26, Folder 511)
    - Copyright documents filed by Cooper's descendents, 1851-1860 (Box 26, Folder 512)
  - Financial Records
    - Accounts for ship Union and articles of agreement for the charter and outfits of the ship, 1819-1821 (Box 27, Folder 513)
      Notebook of voyage no. 2 in 1820 and various financial documents, not in Cooper's handwriting
      Agreement in unidentified handwriting and signed by James Fenimore Cooper and Charles T. Dering
      Union (Whaler), Sag Harbor, New York
    - Account book, 1817-1823 (Box 27, Folder 514)
      In the handwriting of James Fenimore Cooper and Susan De Lancey Cooper
    - Accounts with printers and publishers, 1824-1846 (Box 27, Folder 515)
      Accounts include: John Miller, Robert McDermott, Clayton and Van, Giuseppe Molini, John Fagan, and H.E. Phinney
    - Charles Wiley promissory notes, 1825-1826 (Box 27, Folder 516)
    - Drafts, or cheques, on Cooper's English publishers, Colburn and Bentley, 1829-1833 (Box 27, Folder 517)
    - Accounts relating to estate of William Cooper, 1792-1834 (Box 27, Folder 518)
    - Bills, accounts, and receipts, 1812-1839 (Box 27, Folder 519-523)
    - Bills, accounts, and receipts, 1840-1851, undated (Box 28, Folder 524-530)
    - Bills, accounts, and receipts of Paul Fenimore Cooper, 1851-1857 (Box 29, Folder 531-532)
  - Other Papers
    - Warrant appointing Cooper midshipman in Navy of the United States, 1802 and 1808
      Signed by Thomas Jefferson
      Accompanied by printed document on "The Uniform Dress of the Captains and Certain Other Officers of the Navy of the United States" (1802)
    - Document appointing Cooper paymaster of the fourth Division of Infantry, 1818
    - Document appointing Cooper Quarter Master of the fourth Division of Infantry, 1819
    - Letter patent appointing Cooper Consul of Lyons (France), 1826 May 10
      Signed by John Quincy Adams
    - Visas, travel documents, and other documents relating to Cooper's work as Consul, 1826-1833
    - Passport for James Fenimore Cooper and family, 1828-1832
    - Documents including leases for residences in France, Italy, and New York, and relating to travel while Cooper was a Consul, 1826-1832 (Box 29, Folder 533)
    - Report cards and other material relating to the education of Anne Charlotte Cooper and Caroline Cooper while in Europe, 1827-1831 (Box 29, Folder 534)
    - Calling cards, circa 1833 (Box 29, Folder 535-537)
    - Certificates of membership in various associations, 1817-1831, undated
      Associations include: Westchester Agricultural Society, National Academy of Design, Maryland Historical Society, American Bible Society, American Philosophical Society, Georgia Historical Society, and Societas Philomathoon in Collegio Concordiae Schenectadiae
    - Petition on behalf of widow of Samuel Cromwell, Margaret Cromwell, signed by James Fenimore Cooper and other Cooperstown residents, 1842 (Box 29, Folder 538)
    - Notes belonging to Susan Fenimore Cooper, 1866-1904, undated (Box 29, Folder 539)
      Includes directions regarding her death and funeral arrangements, handwritten copy of poems (including "Prayer Before and After Confirmation") and other writings
    - Note with "Nancy's receipt [recipe] for yeast", undated (Box 29, Folder 540)
    - Certificate appointing Richard Fenimore Cooper Commissioner of Taxes, 1800
    - Certificates belonging to Richard Cooper, 1837-1850
      Contains certificates granting Cooper permission to practice law and marriage certificate for Richard Cooper and Maria Frances Fenimore Cooper
    - Documents relating to Marmaduke Cooper, 1861-1864
      Contains certificates appointing Cooper to military posts, military orders, and documents relating to Cooper's death
  - Printed Material
    - Maps to accompany various novels by Cooper engraved by A.M. Perrot, undated
    - Illustrations from The Pioneers, The Prairie, The Spy from etchings by F.O.C. Darley, undated
      Includes clipping of painting "Scene from the Spy" by William Dunlap
    - Maps of Europe, 1829-1830
    - "An Act to amend the Laws relating to Dramatic Literary Property", 1833 (Box 29, Folder 541)
    - Engravings and lithographs of New York City, undated
    - Engravings and lithographs of various buildings (largely asylums) and of drawing portraying execution of Lady Jane Grey, undated (Box 29, Folder 542)
    - Programs, brochures, and ephemera relating to Cooper, 1940-1975, undated (Box 29, Folder 543-544)
  - Clippings
    Includes articles about Cooper and Cooper's letters to the editor
    - Albany Journal, 1841-1842
      "J. Fennimore Cooper and His Libels" and "Mr. Fennimore Cooper and His Libel Suits"
    - Alexander's Messenger, 1839
    - American Advocate, 1850
      Article regarding default on payment due for Abner Wright's mortgage
    - The Attica Democrat, 1839
      Article regarding Cooper's libel suits
    - Ballston Spa Gazette, 1842
      "Wholesale 'Cooperage'"
    - Binghamton Phoenix, 1817
      Five mortage sales announcements
    - Boston Journal, 1842
    - Chenango Telegraph, 1837
      "'Three Mile Point' and J. Fenimore Cooper"
    - Commercial Chronicle and Daily Marylander, 1839
      "Cooper and the Press"
    - Daily Plebeian, 1843
      "Commodores Perry and Elliot-Battle on Lake Erie"
    - The Evening Post, 1838-1852
      Commentary on Mr. McKenzie's Life of Perry
    - The Evening Signal, 1840
      "The Pathfinder by James F. Cooper"
    - The Family Magazine, 1836 (Box 29, Folder 545)
      "A View of Cooperstown"
    - Fort Plain Journal, 1839
      "The Libel Suit"
    - Freeman's Journal, 1837-1846
      Letter to the editor from Cooper regarding title of ownership of an estate; letter to editor from Cooper in response to a series of articles critiquing The History of the Navy of the United States of America; letter to editor from Auburn (Cayuga co.) Tocsin regarding Cooper's libel suits
    - Gleason's Pictorial Drawing-Room Companion, 1851
      Obituary
    - The Gospel Messenger, 1851-1852
    - Harper's Weekly, 1871, 1874
      "Memories of Distinguished Authors. James Fenimore Cooper"
    - The Illustrated American News, 1851 September 27
    - The Illustrated London News, 1853, 1880
    - Leslie's Monthly, 1872 (Box 29, Folder 546)
      "J. Fenimore Cooper"
    - Madison County Eagle, 1841
    - Morning Courier and New-York Enquirer, 1841, 1843
      "Principles Not Men" commentary on Cooper; "Cooper and His Libel Suits"; letter to the Editor by Cooper
    - Morning Signal, 1840
      Article criticizing Cooper
    - The National Gazette, 1832-1840
      Two letters to the editor by Cooper; article about the battle of Lake Erie controversy
    - New England Galaxy, 1826
      "The Last of the Mohicans"
    - New Era, 1839
      "Mr. Cooper"
    - The New World, undated
      "Fenimore Cooper's Libels on America and Americans"
    - The New Yorker, 1839-1840
      " Eve Effingham by James Fenimore Cooper"
    - New York American, 1839, 1842
      "The Handsome Effingham"; letter to the editor from R.M.T.H. about "the evil effect of pirate Novels"
    - New-York Commercial Advertiser, 1833-1840
      "Cooper's Naval History"; letter to the editor about Cooper; "More Libels"
    - New-York Daily Tribune, 1841-1843
      Annotated by Richard Cooper
    - New York Herald, 1853
      "Cooper House, Cooperstown, Ostego County, New York"
    - The New York Journal of Commerce and Gazette, 1840
      "Prosecutions for Libel"
    - The New York Mirror, 1828-1841
      Multiple articles about Cooper's work
    - New York Sunday Morning News, 1839
      Annotated by J. Head; "Commodore Elliot"
    - The New York Times, 1835, 1839
      Commentary criticizing Cooper; correspondence to J.D. Elliot from N. Towson
    - The Niagara Courier, 1839
      "Fenimore Cooper"
    - Niles' Register, 1834 (Box 29, Folder 547)
    - Northampton Review, 1851
      "Foster -- The Original Cooper's 'Leatherstocking'"
    - The Otsego Republican, 1853
    - Pennsylvania Inquirer and Daily Courier, 1839
    - Philadelphia, 1804
      "American Squadron Off Tripoli"
    - Plattsburgh Whig, 1837
    - Portland Advertiser and Plainfield Union, 1839
      Review of Cooper's "A Naval History of the United States"; "First American Naval Achievement"
    - Public Ledger, 1840
    - Putnam's Magazine, 1853 (Box 29, Folder 548)
      "The Homes of American Authors"
    - The Radiator, 1848
    - The Recorder, 1879
      Letter to the editor about Cooper; "Enoch Crosby. Further Evidence That He Was the Hero of Cooper's Spy"; letter to the editor regarding article about Enoch Crosby
    - Wayne County Whig, 1841
      Article about the Geneva College commencement
    - Utica Daily Gazette and Weekly Ledger, 1848, 1840
      "The People vs. Mary Barrows"
    - Clippings regarding foreclosure of Cooper family home Otsego Hall, 1854 (Box 29, Folder 549)
    - Various clippings about Cooper, 1928-1972, undated (Box 29, Folder 550)
- Art and Objects, 1830-1854; : IV.; 0.42; (1 box)
  The series is organized into two subseries: Art and Objects.
  Engraved portraits of Cooper, dating from roughly 1820 to 1851, are included in the Art subseries along with a portrait of Gilbert du Motier Marquis de Lafayette and a published sketch of the Cooper family home, Otsego Hall.
  Various objects relating to Cooper's writing, such as a travel desk and writing implements, represent the tools of Cooper's profession. Other objects include a box (made from wood salvaged from the ship Endeavour ), two chess sets, and a writing desk presented to General Andrew Jackson by the citizens of Boston, which was bequeathed to Cooper by Grenville T. Winthrop in 1846.
  - Art
    - Portraits of James Fenimore Cooper
      - circa 1820-1830, undated (Box 29, Folder 551)
        Photograph of painting by John Wesley Jarvis
      - circa 1827, 1847 (Box 29, Folder 552)
        After lithograph by Amélie Kautz De Lacepede
      - 1828, undated (Box 29, Folder 553)
        Photograph of bust by P.J. David D'Angers
      - 1830 (Box 29, Folder 554)
        Engraved after painting by Lizinska-Aimee-Zoe de Mirbel
      - 1831
        Lithograph by Engelmann after Julien Leopold Boilly
      - 1833 (Box 29, Folder 555)
        Engraved by E. Seriven after painting by John Wesley Jarvis published in The National Portrait Gallery of Distinguished Americans (1834)
      - 1833, undated (Box 29, Folder 556)
        Photograph of medal
      - circa 1833, undated
        After lithograph by Antoine Maurin
      - 1835 (Box 29, Folder 557)
        Engraved by Steendr van H.J. Backer te Dordt
      - 1844 (Box 29, Folder 558)
        Engraved for the Democratic Review by J.B. Forrest from a daguerrotype miniature by H. Chilton
      - circa 1844, undated
        Engraved by R.W. Dodson after picture by G. Blanchard
      - 1850, undated (Box 29, Folder 559)
        Engraved by Bobbett and Edmonds after dageurreotype by Mathew Brady
        Includes drawing of Otsego Hall by Miss Cooper
      - 1850, undated
        Various engravings after dageurreotype by Mathew Brady
        Engravers include: J.C. Buttre and H.B. Hall
      - 1850, undated
        Engraving by W.E. Marshall after painting by Charles Loring Elliott, which is after daguerreotype by Mathew B. Brady
      - 1854 (Box 29, Folder 560)
        Bust of Cooper from Greenough's monument published in Gleason's Pictorial Drawing-Room Companion (vol. 6, no. 25, June 24, p. 388)
      - Various reproductions of images of Cooper, from youth to old age, undated (Box 29, Folder 561)
      - Undated (Box 29, Folder 562)
        Includes images engraved by Antoine Johannot for Furne, After painting by Alonzo Chappel published in National Portrait Gallery of Eminent Americans (1862), and clippings from newspapers
    - Portraits of Others
      - Lafayette, Gilbert du Motier Marquis de, undated (Box 29, Folder 563)
        Engraved by Cyprien Jacquemin (circa 1840)
  - Objects
    - Travel desk owned and used by Cooper, undated
      Wood; 20 x 11 x 6.5 in.
    - Desk set, undated
      Metal and glass; 11 x 7 x 3 in.
    - Box made from the ship Endeavor, undated
      Wood; 3 x 6.5 x 5 in.
    - Chess sets, undated
      Wood; 5 x 7 x 4 in.
    - Travel desk owned by General Andrew Jackson
      Wood, brass, leather, and fabric; 9 x 22 x 12.5 in.
      The desk was presented to General Andrew Jackson by the citizens of Boston, and bequeathed to Cooper by Grenville T. Winthrop. A letter dated January 4, 1846 from his son Washington L. Winthrop, notifying Cooper of the bequest, is in Box 4, folder 95.
- Oversize and Other Storage, 6.68; (7 boxes) + 20 broadside folders + 4 objects
  - Oversize
    - The Headsman, draft, holograph, 2 pages from chapters 30 and 31, before 1843 and 1874 (Box 30, Folder 564)
    - The Heidenmauer: or, The Benedictines, draft, holograph, corrected, incomplete, before 1832 (Box 30, Folder 565-566)
    - Home as Found, Reviews reprinted in The New Yorker and articles on the libel case against Webb, printed versions, 1839 (Box 30, Folder 567)
    - The Prairie, draft, holograph, in hand of an amanuensis with corrections by Cooper, chapters 21-25, 27-34, incomplete, before 1827 (Box 30, Folder 568-575)
    - "No Steamboat: A Vision," draft, holograph, corrected, incomplete, before 1843 (Box 30, Folder 576)
    - De Witt, R.V., "The Annesley System of Naval Architecture," The New York State Mechanic, printed version, 1842 (Box 30, Folder 577)
    - Leeds, Gurdon J., "Report of the Nautical Committee of the American Institute on Annesley's System of Ship Building," printed version, 1843 (Box 30, Folder 578)
    - WAMBA, "Reply to Cooper's Attack Upon Sir Walter Scott," The New Yorker, 1838 December 29 (Box 30, Folder 579)
    - Warrant appointing Cooper midshipman in Navy of the United States, 1802-1808 (Box 30, Folder 580)
    - Passport for James Fenimore Cooper and family, 1828-1832 (Box 30, Folder 581)
    - Certificate appointing Richard Fenimore Cooper Commissioner of Taxes, 1800 (Box 30, Folder 582)
    - Certificates belonging to Richard Cooper, 1837-1850 (Box 30, Folder 583)
    - Maps to accompany various novels by Cooper engraved by A.M. Perrot, undated (Box 30, Folder 584)
    - Illustrations from The Pioneers, The Prairie, The Spy from etchings by F.O.C. Darley, undated (Box 30, Folder 585)
    - Engravings and lithographs of New York City, undated (Box 30, Folder 586)
    - The Illustrated American News, 1851 September 27 (Box 30, Folder 587)